Guide to the Gerald M. Meier Papers, 1928-2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gerald M. Meier papers 1928-2003
Meier, Gerald M.
7.75 linear feet Extent: 5400 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00884
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Gerald M. Meier Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1999 and 2010.
Biographical Note
1923, Feb. 9 Born, Tacoma, Wash.
1947 Reed College: B.A. (Social Science) Phi Beta Kappa
1948-1950, 1951-1952 Rhodes Scholar
1952 University of Oxford: B. Litt. (Economics)
1953 Harvard University: Ph.D. (Economics)
1954, Oct. 23 Married Gilda Slote; four children (David, Daniel, Jeremy, and Andrew)
1954-1959 Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.), Assistant Professor and Professor of Economics
1955-1956 Yale University, Visiting Lecturer
1957 Published Economic Development
1956-1957, 1958-1959 Yale University, Visiting Associate Professor
1957-1958 Guggenheim Fellow
1959 Wesleyan University: M.A. (Honoris Causa)
1959-1963 Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.), Chester D. Hubbard Professor of Economics
1959-1961 Yale University, Visiting Professor
1961-1962 Brookings National Research Professorship
1963 Published International Trade and Development
1963-1992 Stanford University, Konosuke Matsushita Professor of International Economics and Policy Analysis, 1963-92,
1964 Published Leading Issues in Development Economics
1968 Published The International Economics of Development
1970, 1976 Published Leading Issues In Economic Development; Studies In International Poverty
1973 Published Problems of a Trade Policy
1974 Published Problems of Cooperation for Development
1974, 1982 Published Problems of a World Monetary Order
1974-1975 Rockefeller Foundation Research Grant
1977 Published Employment, Trade, and Development
1980 Published International Economics: Theory of Policy
1983 Published Pricing Policy for Development Management
1984 Published Emerging from Poverty: The Economics that Really Matters
1985 Co-editor, Pioneers in Development
1986 Published Financing Asian Development: Performance and Prospects
1989 Published Asian Development: Economic Success And Policy Lessons
1992 Stanford University, Professor Emeritus
1998 Published The International Environment Of Business: Competition And Governance In The Global Economy
Collection Overview
The papers of Gerald M. Meier span the years 1928-2003, with the bulk of the materials from 1941-2001. These materials document the growth of Meier's career from a student of economics to an academic economist. This collection includes personal and professional correspondence; lectures; course notes taken as a student or developed for his lectures on international economic relations; syllabi, reading lists, exams, and other course materials; materials relating to conferences attended; published writings; and audiotapes of interviews relating to the evolution of development economics. The Correspondence Series is largely of a professional nature, and is chiefly concerned with international and development economics. Prominent among Meier's correspondents were Peter Bauer, Gottfried Haberler, W.A. Lewis, Hla Myint, Paul Rosenstein-Rodan, W.W. Rostow, Dudley Seers, H.W. Singer, and Paul Streeten.
Many of Meier's major publications are represented in the Writings and Speeches Series. These include Economic Development, Emerging from Poverty, The International Economics of Development, International Trade and Development, Leading Issues in Development Economics, Pioneers in Development, and the Problems series of books. Though there are more than a few folders containing materials on conferences attended by Meier, by and large the Subject Series contains a great deal of course materials. From his days as a student, there are notes, exams, syllabi, reading lists, and bibliographies from Reed College, Harvard University, and University of Oxford concerning courses taken under Edward Chamberlin, Gottfried Haberler, John Hicks, Wassily Leontief, and others. Also, there is material representing the several law courses Meier enrolled in at Yale University and Stanford University. Among the lecture notes from Williams College, Wesleyan University, Yale University, and Stanford University, there are also syllabi, exams, and reading lists representing his tenure as a professor. Of particular note are the several folders concerning Meier's role in the genesis and growth of the College of Social Studies at Wesleyan University.
Accession (2010-0211) also contains work from Meier's career, including reprints of his articles (dated 1949-1984) and materials from his lectures and presentations on development economics (dated 1986-2002). Also included are some miscellaneous correspondence, grant proposals, and book reviews. A large portion of the accession relates to Meier's writings, including his drafts and correspondence from several books, especially Frontiers of Development Economics (published 2001) and Development: Biography of a Subject (published 2004). Another section of interest is Meier's collection of materials on the career of John Hicks, a 1972 Nobel prize-winning economist. The collection includes article reprints written by Hicks, some clippings about his life, and an undated, unpublished manuscript titled The Theory of Demand and the Theory of Welfare.
Subject Headings
Hla Myint, U.; Meier, Gerald M.; Chamberlin, Edward,; Haberler, Gottfried,; Hicks, John Richard, Sir,; Leontief, Wassily W.,; Lewis, W. Arthur (William Arthur),; Rostow, W. W. (Walt Whitman),; Seers, Dudley; Singer, Hans Wolfgang,; Streeten, Paul; Bauer, P. T. (Péter Tamás); Rosenstein-Rodan, P. N.; Stanford University; Williams College; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.); Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.) -- History; Yale University; International economic relations; Development economics; Development economics -- History; Economic development; Economists -- United States; Economists -- United States -- Correspondence; Economics -- History -- 20th century; Economics -- Study and teaching; Economics -- Study and teaching -- United States; Economics -- Study and teaching -- England -- Oxford; Developing countries -- Economic conditions; Audiocassettes
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1949-1988
  Consists of letters written to Meier by economists, educators, businessmen, and officials of governments and organizations. The collection is primarily professional, with few instances of communications with personal friends and family. Arranged into alphabetical and chronological groups.
  - Alphabetical (Box C1)
    - Asian Development Bank, 1981 (Box C1)
    - Bauer, Peter, 1983-1984 (Box C1)
    - Hirschman, Albert, 1983 (Box C1)
    - Law and Economics, 1964-1975 (Box C1)
    - Lewis, W.A., 1983 (Box C1)
    - Myint, Hla, 1967-1971 (Box C1)
    - Myrdal, Gunnar, 1983-1988 (Box C1)
    - Overseas Development Council, 1970 (Box C1)
    - Rosenstein-Rodan, Paul, 1982-1983 (Box C1)
    - Rostow, W.W., 1982-1983 (Box C1)
    - Shaw-McKinnon, 1970-1971 (Box C1)
    - Singer, H.W., 1983 (Box C1)
    - Streeten, Paul, 1983 (Box C1)
    - Tinbergen, Jan, 1982-1983 (Box C1)
    - Wesleyan Appointment, 1953-1955 (Box C1)
    - Yale Law, 1963-1975 (Box C1)
  - Chronological
    - 1949-1954 (Box C1)
    - 1954-1959 (Box C1)
    - 1955-1959 (Box C1)
    - 1958, 1977-1979 (Box C1)
    - 1960-1962 (Box C1)
    - 1960-1963 (Box C1)
    - 1963-1964 (Box C1)
    - 1965 (Box C1)
    - 1966 (Box C1)
    - 1967-1969 (Box C1)
    - 1970-1972 (Box C1)
    - 1971-1983 (Box C1)
    - 1973-1975 (Box C1)
    - 1976-1979 (Box C1)
    - 1980-1982 (Box C1)
    - 1983-1985 (Box C1)
    - 1986 (Box C1)
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1949-1987
  Meier's writings and speeches focus on international economics and the economics of development. The materials, consisting mainly of offprints and reprints, are arranged into alphabetical groups by title of publication. There is also supporting material (correspondence, notes, drafts, referee letters, reviews, and audiotapes) concerning several of his major publications.
  - Accelerating Development in Poor Countries, 1956 (Box WS1)
  - La aceleración del desarrollo en los países pobres, 1958 (Box WS1)
  - Analyzing the Risk of Lending to Developing Countries, 1983 (Box WS1)
  - On 'Appropriate' Policy Technology for Development, 1977 (Box WS1)
  - Book Reviews, 1953-1980 (Box WS1)
  - Book Reviews, Pioneers in Development, Emerging from Poverty, Leading Issues in Development Economics, 1982-1987 (Box WS1)
  - The Bretton Woods Agreement: Twenty-Five Years After, 1971 (Box WS1)
  - Comment on the Terms of Trade and Economic Development, 1958 (Box WS1)
  - La crisi della programmazione nei paesi in via di sviluppo, 1970 (Box WS1)
  - La crisis de la planeación en los países en desarrollo, 1970 (Box WS1)
  - A Critique of the New British Monopoly Act, 1950 (Box WS1)
  - Development Decade in Perspective, 1971 (Box WS1)
  - Development Without Employment, 1969 (Box WS1)
  - Economic Development, Reviews, 1957 (Box WS1)
  - Economic Development of Export Economics, 1959 (Box WS1)
  - Economic Development and the Transfer Mechanism: Canada, 1895-1913, undated (Box WS1)
  - Emerging from Poverty
    - Bretton Woods History for Introduction, 1981-1983 (Box WS1)
    - Letters, 1980-1983 (Box WS1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1979-1983 (Box WS1)
  - Externality Law and Market Safeguards: Applications in the GATT Multilateral Trade Negotiations, 1977 (Box WS1)
  - Export Stimulation, Import Substitution and Latin American Development, 1961 (Box WS1)
  - Foreign Aid: Economic Aspects, 1968 (Box WS1)
  - Free Trade and Development Economics, 1968 (Box WS1)
  - International Economic Reform: Collected Papers of Emile Despres, Correspondence and Reviews, 1974-1975 (Box WS1)
  - International Economics of Development, Correspondence and Reviews, 1966-1970 (Box WS1)
  - International Economics Law and Development, Chapter 1, miscellaneous notes, undated (Box WS1)
  - International Trade and Development, Correspondence and Reviews, 1961-1963 (Box WS1)
  - International Trade and International Inequality, 1958 (Box WS1)
  - The 'Jamaica Agreement,' International Monetary Reform, and the Developing Countries, 1976 (Box WS1)
  - Leading Issues in Economic Development
    - Correspondence and Reviews, 1970-1976 (Box WS1)
    - Referee Letters, 1963 (Box WS1)
    - Reviews, 1964-1966 (Box WS1)
    - Oxford University Press, 1962-1965 (Box WS1)
  - Legal-Economic Problems of Private Foreign Investment in Developing Countries, 1966 (Box WS1)
  - Long Period Determinants of Britain's Terms of Trade, 1880-1913, 1952-1953 (Box WS1)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box WS1)
  - Myrdal on Commercial Policy of Underdeveloped Countries, 1958 (Box WS1)
  - A Note on the Theory of Comparative Costs and Long Period Developments, 1952 (Box WS1)
  - Pioneers in Development
    - Correspondence, 1982-1986 (Box WS1)
    - Correspondence on early courses in Development Economics for Introduction, 1983-1984 (Box WS1)
    - Dudley Seers, 1982-1983 (Box WS1)
    - Audiotapes of seminars at World Bank, 1982 (Box WS1)
  - The Poverty of Nations, 1957 (Box WS1)
  - The Problem of Limited Economic Development, 1953 (Box WS1)
  - El Problema del desarrollo económico limitado, 1960 (Box WS1)
  - Problems Series, Correspondence and Reviews, 1970-1976 (Box WS1)
  - Progress and Problems of the Development Decade, 1966 (Box WS1)
  - The Role of an Expert Advisory Group in a Young Government, 1965 (Box WS1)
  - Some Questions about Growth Economics: Comment, 1954 (Box WS1)
  - Sviluppo senza occupazione, 1970 (Box WS1)
  - Symposium on the Report of the Trade and Tariffs Commission, 1960 (Box WS1)
  - The Theory of Comparative Costs Reconsidered, 1949 (Box WS1)
  - The Tokyo Round of Multilateral Trade Negotiations and the Developing Countries, 1980 (Box WS1)
  - The Trade Matrix: Comment, 1948 (Box WS1)
  - UNCTAD Proposals for International Economic Reform, 1967 (Box WS1)
  - U.S. Foreign Economic Policies, 1980 (Box WS1)
- Subject Series, 1941-1998
  The bulk of this series consists of files relating to conferences attended and to course materials. The latter files contain bibliographies, syllabi, reading lists, exams, and notes, both for undergraduate and graduate courses and, likewise, for both courses attended as a student and courses taught as a professor. The schools represented in the collection are Harvard, Oxford, Reed, Stanford, Wesleyan, Williams, and Yale. Arranged alphabetically.
  - IV World Congress, Budapest, 1974 (Box S1)
  - American Council of Learned Societies Annual Meeting, 1957 (Box S1)
  - Africa Trip, 1982 (Box S1)
  - Agricultural Development Council (ADC) Conference, 1965 (Box S1)
  - Bellagio Study and Conference Center, 1981 (Box S1)
  - Cairo, 1982 (Box S1)
  - Cambridge Conference
    - 1965 (Box S1)
    - 1970 (Box S1)
    - 1972 (Box S1)
  - Center for Economic Policy Research, 1986 (Box S1)
  - China Lecture for World Bank, 1984 (Box S1)
  - Committee for the Study of Mankind, 1960 (Box S1)
  - Conference on the International Economic and Financial Systems, 1995 (Box S1)
  - Conference on International Economics, 1956 (Box S1)
  - Conselho Administrativo de Defesa Econômica (Brazil) CADE, 1972 (Box S1)
  - The Content of Education for Accelerated Agricultural Development, 1965 (Box S1)
  - Development: International Law and Economics Symposium, 1967 (Box S1)
  - Economic Development and World Debt, 1987 (Box S1)
  - Ethics and International Relations, 1973 (Box S1)
  - European Logistics Management Program, 1971 (Box S1)
  - Globalization, Development or Underdevelopment, 1997 (Box S1)
  - Goodyear International Management Seminar, 1973 (Box S1)
  - Hicks Fechtschrift - Free Trade and Development Economics, 1966-1967 (Box S1)
  - Institute of Development Studies
    - 1966-1968, n.d (Box S1)
    - 1968, 1971 (Box S1)
    - 1969 (Box S1)
  - Instituto Peruano de Administración de Empresas (IPAE), 1973 (Box S1)
  - International Center for Economic Growth (ICEG), 1994 (Box S1)
  - International Conference on Economic History, 1960 (Box S1)
  - International Symposium of Nihon University, 1996 (Box S1)
  - Jamaica Trip, 1970, 1983 (Box S1)
  - Korea Institute for International Economic Policy (KIEP), Korea, 1995 (Box S1)
  - Latin-American - U.S. Economic Interactions, Texas, 1973 (Box S1)
  - Law and Development Conference, University of Wisconsin, 1968 (Box S1)
  - Law and Economics Committee, 1968-1971 (Box S1)
  - Malawi - Underdevelopment and Economics, undated (Box S1)
  - Merrill Center for Economics, 1955 (Box S1)
  - Miscellaneous Conferences, 1956-1986 and undated (Box S1)
  - Moral Aspects of War, Power, and Economic Involvement, undated (Box S1)
  - Moscow Meeting, 1988 (Box S1)
  - Nyasaland Conference
    - 1961-1997 and undated, (4 folders) (Box S1)
    - 1983 and undated (Box S1)
  - Pakistan, 1958 (Box S1)
  - Peru, 1972 (Box S1)
  - Rome/Vatican, 1993 (Box S1)
  - Schools
    - Harvard University
      - Course Notes, 1947-1948 (Box S1)
      - International Economics, Bibliographies, 1951-1952 (Box S1)
      - International Economics, Haberler, 1947, (3 folders) (Box S2)
      - International Economics, Haberler and Balogh, 1947-1948, (3 folders) (Box S2)
      - International Economics, Miscellaneous Seminars and Lectures, 1948, (4 folders) (Box S2)
      - International Economics, Notes, 1947-1948, (2 folders) (Box S2)
      - Lectures, 1948, 1950-1951 (Box S2)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Attendance at Miscellaneous Lectures, 1960-1987 and undated (Box S2)
      - Course Reading Lists, 1947-1955 and undated (Box S2)
      - Exams, 1947-1952 (Box S2)
      - Exams, 1948-1965 and undated (Box S2)
      - J.M. Finnis - Jurisprudence, 1974 (Box S2)
      - Law and Economics Lectures, 1958-1978 (Box S2)
      - Lectures (Hicks, Haberler, Chamberlin, Leontief) and Exams, 1947-1951 and undated (Box S2)
      - Lectures, Oxford 1948-1949, Harvard 1947, 1950 (Box S2)
      - Miscellaneous Lectures Attended, 1946-1994 and undated (Box S2)
      - Miscellaneous Syllabi and Exams, 1971-1982 and undated (Box S2)
      - Miscellaneous Syllabi and Handouts, 1952-1968 (Box S2)
      - Syllabi for Various Economics Courses, 1953-1972 and undated (Box S2)
    - Reed College (Portland, Or.), 1941-1942 (Box S3)
    - Stanford University
      - Courses Materials, International Law and Development, 1964-1972 (Box S3)
      - Course Notes, 1964 and undated (Box S3)
      - Courses, 1963 (Box S3)
      - Econ 216 Despres and Meier, 1963-1964 (Box S3)
      - International Economics Exams, 1963-1968 (Box S3)
      - Price Analysis, 1964 (Box S3)
      - Price System, 1969-1970, (2 folders) (Box S3)
      - Tort Law, 1975, (2 folders) (Box S3)
    - University of Oxford
      - Lectures, 1948-1949 (Box S3)
      - Lectures and Journals, 1948-1985 (Box S3)
      - Lectures and Journals, 1958 (Box S3)
    - Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)
      - College of Social Studies
        - 1958-1994, undated (Box S3)
        - 1960 (Box S3)
        - 1971, undated (Box S3)
        - 1994-1998 (Box S3)
        - Econ Tutorials, 1960-1961 (Box S3)
      - Courses, 1953-1963 and undated, (2 folders) (Box S3)
      - Courses, 1959 and undated (Box S3)
      - Econ 2 Lectures, 1959 (Box S3)
      - Econ 31-32 Lecture Notes, 1958-1959 (Box S3)
      - Economic Theory Reading Lists, 1954-1959 (Box S3)
    - Williams College
      - 1985 (Box S3)
      - Courses, 1952-1954 (Box S3)
      - Econ 1, 1952 and Econ 3-4, 1953-1954 (Box S3)
    - Yale University
      - Constitution Law, 1976 (Box S3)
      - Contracts and Torts, Leff and Calabresi, 1976 (Box S3)
      - Course Notes, 1953-1956 and undated (Box S3)
      - Courses, 1955-1957 (Box S3)
      - International Welfare Economics and International Law, 1973-1986, (2 folders) (Box S3)
      - Law and Economics, 1956-1957 (Box S3)
  - Tacoma Sunday Times, undated (Box S3)
  - Top Executive Seminar on International Economic Problems, Tel Aviv, 1974-1975 (Box S3)
  - U.S. - Mexican Financial Relations Conference, 1974 (Box S3)
  - University of Texas – Latin-American Conference, 1973 (Box S3)
  - Zagreb, 1987 (Box S3)
- Oversize Materials Series
  - Subject Subseries
    - Nyasaland Conference, 1962 (Opaperfolder 1)
- Accession (2010-0211), 1928-2003, (2 boxes)
  Accession (2010-0211) (900 items; 1.5 lin. ft.) also contains work from Meier's career, including reprints of his articles (dated 1949-1984) and materials from his lectures and presentations on development economics (dated 1986-2002). Also included are some miscellaneous correspondence, grant proposals, and book reviews. A large portion of the accession relates to Meier's writings, including his drafts and correspondence from several books, especially Frontiers of Development Economics (published 2001) and Development: Biography of a Subject (published 2004). Another section of interest is Meier's collection of materials on the career of John Hicks, a 1972 Nobel prize-winning economist. The collection includes article reprints written by Hicks, some clippings about his life, and an undated, unpublished manuscript titled "The Theory of Demand and the Theory of Welfare."
  - Public speaking, 1986-2002 and undated, (3 folders) (Box A1)
    Materials from Meier's talks, lectures, and presentations throughout the world on social capital, developing countries, and development economics.
  - Miscellaneous publications by Meier, 1949-1984 and undated, (6 folders) (Box A1)
    Arranged chronologically by year. Includes offprint journal articles and book reviews. Several have duplicates.
  - Book manuscripts (Box A1)
    - Pioneers in Development, vols. 1 and 2, 1982-1985 (Box A1)
    - The World Beyond the Firm, 1992-1996 (Box A1)
    - Frontiers of Development Economics, 1999-2001, (3 folders) (Box A1)
      Correspondence, notes, and chapter drafts.
    - Leading Issues in Economic Development, 1996-1998 (Box A1)
    - Development: Biography of a Subject, 2001 and undated, (6 folders) (Box A1)
      Proposals, pre-reviews, notes, drafts of chapters.
    - Unknown titles, undated (Box A1)
  - Correspondence, 1947-2003 and undated, (2 folders) (Box A1)
  - Book reviews and Grants, 1978-1989 and undated (Box A1)
  - John Hicks materials (Box A1)
    - Article reprints, 1928-1974, (2 folders) (Box A1)
    - Unpublished manuscript: "The Theory of Demand and the Theory of Welfare," undated (Box A1)
    - Clippings, 1950s-1989 (Box A1)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1992 (Box A2)
  - Writings by others (Box A2)
  - Sir Arthur Lewis lecture, 2002 (Box A2)
  - Memorial clippings (Box A2)